<?xml version="1.0"?> 
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY appname "Harmonic">
<!ENTITY app "<application>Harmonic</application>">
<!ENTITY appversion "0.1.0">
<!ENTITY manrevision "0.1.0">
<!ENTITY date "March 2011">
]>
<article id="index" lang="en">
  <articleinfo><title>&appname; Manual</title>
    <abstract role="description">
      <para>
        &app; is a program for performing harmonic analysis (e.g. Fourier Analysis).
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <copyright>
      <year>2011</year>
      <holder>Paul Childs</holder>
    </copyright>
    <author role="maintainer">
      <firstname>Paul</firstname>
      <surname>Childs</surname>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Foundation for Research and Technology--Hellas</orgname>
        <address>
          <email>pchilds@physics.org</email>
        </address>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>&appname; Manual &manrevision;</revnumber>
        <date>13-03-2011</date>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    <releaseinfo>
      Version &manrevision; documenting &appname; version &appversion;.
    </releaseinfo>
    <legalnotice><title>Copyright</title>
      <para>Copyright (C)  2011  Paul Childs.</para>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
        under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3
        or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
        with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.
        A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
        Free Documentation License".</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>
  <sect1 id="introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
    <para>Use &app; to transform spectral data into the dual domain and analyse the resultant inverse spectrum to extract properties such as fringe visibility, domain shifts and chirp.</para>
    <para>For updates please visit <ulink type="http" url="https://github.com/pchilds/Harmonic">Harmonic's repository</ulink></para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="base"><title>The Base Domain</title>
    <sect2><title>Loading Data</title>
      <para>From the properties menu select the appropriate data format (The list corresponds to the device from which measurements were made). If your device is not listed, send an email of a few sample measurements to the author (listed in the AUTHOR file included with this software) so that future versions may include this device. Also try a number of existing devices listed in case the format is compatible.</para>
      <para> From the file menu select open and choose your file. If the format is correct, the spectrum should display on the plot as expected. If there is irregulaties such as lines that go to (0,0) it is likely that the software is not interpreting the format of the data correctly. Please send a copy of the data file to the author and state which format you had selected. It may still be possible to process the data in spite of such irregularities.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2><title>Navigating the Plots</title>
      <para>Harmonic uses a customised plotting widget for displaying data. For further information and/or feedback see the documentation given in its <ulink type="http" url="https://github.com/pchilds/GtkPlot">repository</ulink>.</para>
      <para>The range of the plot can be zoomed in and out (horizontally and/or vertically) according to the zoom mode selected by clicking on the two boxes in the top right corner of each plot. The box on the left controls whether zooming is to be performed in the horizontal direction only (when two dotted vertical lines are shown), in the vertical direction only (when two dotted horizontal lines are shown) or both horzontally and vertically (A dashed rectangle is shown). The range to zoom over is selecting by clicking at one corner/edge and dragging and releasing at the opposite corner/edge. For convenience, zooming can alternately be perfomed with a single click by toggling the setting in the left box until an X is displayed.</para>
      <para>The box on the right controls whether to zoom in or out (arrows pointing out or in respectively). For the case of zooming in, the resultant image displayed in the plot is the image loosely fitted to the bounding click-drag-release box (loosely as the plot tries to fit the axes range to sensible power of ten multiples of 1, 2 and 5). For the case of zooming out, the resultant image is the extrapolation of shrinking the original entire plot into the bounding click-drag-release box.</para>
      <tip><title>tip</title>
        <para>If e.g you wanted to display more range to the top left of a linear graph then (with zoom out mode set) you would select a bounding box in the bottom right of the plot.</para>
      </tip>
      <para>When batch processing, the results can be displayed as a polar plot, which operates quite similarly. The exception here is due to the wrapping around 360&#xb0; in which case given two azimuthal limits it is ambiguous which segment to take as the range. In order to maintain consistency, the range is thus assumed to flow clockwise from the clicked limit to the released limit. e.g. clicking at 30&#xb0; and dragging to 50&#xb0; will give the large range of -310&#xb0; to 50&#xb0;<footnote><para>50&#xb0; is wrapped around to -310&#xb0; here in order to push the 360&#xb0; discontinuity point outside of the range.</para></footnote> even though the mouse may have taken the shorter path.</para>
      <para>Multiple plots can be displayed and the title/font/size of the axes and their tick label numbers changed by selecting Display Properties in the Properties menu.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2><title>Invert domain?</title>
      <para>One of the options in the Advanced menu is the option to invert the domain. Not to be confused with the inverse domain (whose inverse is calcluated as the Fourier inverse or more general harmonic inverses to be included later) this inverse is calculated as: <inlineequation><mathphrase><emphasis>k</emphasis>=2<emphasis>π</emphasis>/<emphasis>x</emphasis></mathphrase></inlineequation>; useful for converting between domains such as wavelength and wavenumber that have such a relation. As the discrete Harmonic transformations require uniform sampling, the domain is interpolated to ensure this. This feature is yet to be implemented and should not be used yet.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2><title>Selecting windowed regions for transformation</title>
      <para>Windows are defined by the Spectrum Start and Stop values. Multiple windows can be selected by incrementing the j index value to add a new window. If you have inadvertantly added a window that isn't desired you will have to press reset arrays to remove these additional windows and start again. Accurate values for the Start and Stop values can be determined based on the coordinates displayed in the statusbar when holding the mouse over a particular point in the spectrum displayed in the plot.</para>
      <para>If you want to see the transformed results of all the windows on the one plot at the same time select "Multiple plots for Inverse Domain" from Display Properties in the Properties menu.</para>
      <para>The Discrete Fourier (and Wavelet) Transform works most efficiently when acting on a data set with points numbering a power of 2. As such the program will add zero values to either side of the selected windows to reach this. The total number of points is given by 2 to the power of the value entered in "Zero Padding". An added advantage of this approach is that the zero padding acts to interpolate the data in the transformed domain, giving more data points for analysis (of particular importance for accurately determining domain shifts when the peak in the inverse domain is narrow).</para>
      <para>The drawback to this approach is that if the selected window does not go to zero at its start and stop values, the jump will cause ringing in the transformed spectrum. This effect can be reduced using the Offset parameter to subtract from the spectrum prior to zero padding. The offset should be set to the value to which the spectrum goes to at start and stop for the case of devices measured in transmission. For the case of reflection measurements, it is meant to correspond to the value for 100% reflection and has little effect on the results.</para>
      <para id="base_edgecorr">If your spectrum is such that a single offset value cannot match well to all the window edges, a linear correction to each window can be applied by selecting "Apply correction to Window edges" from the Advanced menu. In this case no offset value needs to be specified as the program will automatically determine the correction based on your data. Reflection measurements, however, cannot be corrected in this way and require an offset to be specified.</para>
      <para id="base_autotrack">If this is not the case, but you have a number of data sets where the ideal offset value would vary due to power fluctuations for example, this can be automatically tracked by selecting "Autotrack Offset" from the Advanced menu, which adjust the offset according to changes in the amplitude of the last 16 data points of the entire spectrum. If this region of the spectrum is an unreliable indicator of the 100% level (particularly if e.g. measurents are made in reflection and this is the noise floor) then it is best to avoid using offset tracking. In order to properly initiate offset autotracking, perform one transformation of a file with "Autotrack Offset" deselected (otherwise the reference level of the last 16 points will be zero) and a suitable offset value for this particular spectrum. Then select "Autotrack offset" and perform the subsequent transformations. The offset will automatically change for each spectrum. To reset the reference level used by "Autotrack offset" deslect it and perform a transform.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2><title>Nonlinear compensation</title>
      <para>Harmonic transformations are linear functionals and as such requires the spectrum to also be a linear functional of its constiuent elements in order to perform accurate reconstruction. Apart from the trivial case where only one element is analysed, most systems are in fact nonlinear.</para>
      <para>Measuring the tranmission of several elements in series is the product of their individual transmissions. Where transmission of the elements is defined by a matrix, this product will be a matrix product. This nonlinearity will cause a mixing of the individual harmonic terms; which can result in crosstalk occuring between two individually distinct elements.</para>
      <para>The logarithm provides an isomorphism between scalar multiplication and linear addition: <inlineequation><mathphrase>log(AB)=log(A)+log(B)</mathphrase></inlineequation>. It is thus possible to transform a (scalar) nonlinear system to the linear functional required by the Harmonic transforms by using the logarithmic mapping. This is what is done when selecting "1st order spectral shadowing" for Nonlinear compensation from the advanced menu. This method is, however, a scalar approximation and fails to account for effects such as multiple reflections between elements that occur when the transmission is matrix valued<footnote><para>For a study on the errors of the linear and scalar approximations in the context of optical Bragg reflectors see P. Childs, and Y.B. Liao "On the multiplexed limit capacity of spectrally overlapped continuous wave fibre Bragg grating sensor networks" in J. Opt., Vol. 12, Iss. 1, Jan. (2010) paper 015404.</para></footnote>. Also, as it introduces more computational steps it should be avoided for the simple cases where there is only a single element or situations where the spectrum is actually linear.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2><title>Basis function</title>
      <para>Harmonic transformations are simply dot products with certain basis functions. For the case of the Fourier transform this is the familiar <inlineequation><mathphrase><emphasis>e</emphasis><superscript>-2<emphasis>πixs</emphasis></superscript></mathphrase></inlineequation>, where <emphasis>x</emphasis> and <emphasis>s</emphasis> are the domain variables between which transformation occurs.</para>
      <para>This basis function is, however, not localised and thus is not as ideal for working with localised features. Wavelets are oscillatory functions that have good localisation both in their base domain as well as when transformed. From the Advanced menu select "Basis function:" and then choose a wavelet type to change from the standard Fourier basis (yet to be implemented).</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="inv"><title>The Inverse Domain</title>
    <sect2><title>Selecting windowed regions for transformation</title>
      <para>Similar to the case of the base domain, regions of data can be defined with the "Inverse Spectrum Start" and "Inverse Spectrum Stop" parameters. Values should be given for each window defined by the j index. Multiple windows in the inverse spectrum can be selected with the k index.</para>
      <para> Differences for this case are mainly seen in the triangles parameters. Calculation of phase based values such as domain shifts and chirp is performed as a weighted average over these triangles, which are designed as the best fit to the peaks being analysed (in terms of centre value and width). In this way data at the edge of the triangles, where the magnitude is low (and hence noise in the phase is high), contributes less to the overall result and the reliable data in the centre contributes more.</para>
      <para>Phase shifts in the spectrum can also cause large errors. In this case it may be necessary to limit the start and stop values to a narrower range so as to exclude regions of high phase error rather than unnaturally distorting the triangles.</para>
      <para>The visibility of fringes is referenced against the area given by the peak at zero frequency (DC peak), hence you will have to specify the width of this peak over which to calculate its area (To be consistent with the way in which the triangles are defined, this is the full width which can be determined as twice the frequency at which a line fitted to the DC peak cuts the horizontal axis).</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2><title>Optimise Triangles?</title>
      <para>Triangle optimisation is not yet implemented.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2><title>Interpreting results</title>
      <para>The program will give values for the visibility of fringes and the domain shift (If calculate chirp was selected from the advanced menu, then this will be shown as well).</para>
      <para>The visibility is calculated as the area of the peak selected by the Inverse Spectrum Start and Stop parameters divided by half of the area of the DC peak. This is not the same as the way in which the visibility is defined on a spectrum, but nevertheless provides a more stable reliable meaure of it particularly on heavily modulated signals.</para>
      <para>For real positive valued spectra the visibility takes values between 0 and 1 for zero and full visibility respectively. The measured value is generally lower than the actual value of the device due to factors such as detector bandwidths reducing the magnitude of higher frequency components. Other errors can be introduced, e.g. if the offset isn't correctly set a sinc+delta signal will be added to the transformed signal which will increase the area of the DC peak and reduce the visibility<footnote><para>In cases where the offset is not stable an analysis of just the area of the harmonic peak may be better. Future versions will look to include this option.</para></footnote>.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="batc"><title>Batch Processing</title>
    <sect2><title>Processing</title>
      <para>To run a batch process, first run a test on one of the spectra that will be processed with the parameters that you intend to use throughout the batch process. Then, ensuring that Batch processing is checked in the Advanced menu, from the file menu select open and then select your configuration file or press new to open a window to input the values for one (see the <link linkend="batc_conf">next section</link> for instructions). Select whether to display on a linear or polar scale to graph the results.</para>
      <para>If the offset level is not consistent across the different measurement files, it is possible to automatically correct for changes in the overall amplitude by selecting "Autotrack Offset" from the Advanced menu (see what is documented earlier about <link linkend="base_autotrack">autotracking</link> for instructions on its use). Note that if "Apply correction to Window edges" is also selected, autotracking has no effect as the edge correction routine needs no offset value.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="batc_conf"><title>The configuration file</title>
      <para>After pressing "File->open" then "New" a configuration file can be created by adjusting the spin button to the value of the variable corresponding to the first file. Then press "Add another file" to select the file. Repeat this process over all required files that make up your measurement set and then press "Save".</para>
      <warning><title>warning</title>
        <para>It is important that the files be ordered properly for display in the plot (lower to higher values). It is also necessary to select the spin value before the filename as the value is fixed once the file is selected (fixing this problem will be addressed in future releases).</para>
      </warning>
      <para>Configuration files can also be written manually. The format for the files is 2 columns of tab delimited data, the first being a numerical value for the variable parameter that differs from file to file, and the second being the file name.</para>
      <tip><title>tip</title>
        <para>Note that when writing your own configuration file the format for the file name must include the full path to locate the file.</para>
      </tip>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="save"><title>Exporting Results</title>
    <sect2><title>Saving data</title>
      <para>To save data switch to the notebook page which represents the results you want to save and press save from the file menu. Once you have chosen a file to save to, you will then be given options if available on what subset of your results to save. Select the desired option and press save.</para>
      <para>The format of the data will be tab-delimited divided into categorised columns that repeat over the variable (J or K) over which iteration was desired for the case of batch processed data, or over the variable alternate to the row variable for the case of data from a single file.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2><title>Saving graphs</title>
      <para>Select the tab of the desired graph to save and ensure that the graph looks how you want to print it (zoomed to the right scale and with axes labelled and sized as set up in Properties->Display Properties). From the file menu choose print and type in a file name ending in .eps for Encapsulated Postscript. EPS is a vector image format that allows for easy scaling without loss of image quality. EPS is the format used for publication by LaTEX and is chosen here to allow the smooth transfer of data results to a publication ready format without the need of an intermediary step of editing figures.</para>
      <para>To convert to another format, such as tiff, use an image editing program such as GIMP to first scale the image to the desired size and then save in the new format.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="xmpl"><title>Examples</title>
    <sect2><title>Processing a measurement of a single Interferometric element</title>
      <para>A single Fabry Perot element has a sinusoidal spectrum over wavenumber <inlineequation><mathphrase><emphasis>k</emphasis>=<emphasis>λ</emphasis>/2<emphasis>π</emphasis></mathphrase></inlineequation>). If measurements are made over wavelength then select "Advanced->Invert Domain". Otherwise if measurements are actually made over wavenumber then leave it unchecked. Select "Advanced->Nonlinear Compensation:->None" and leave all remaining items in the Advanced menu deslected.</para>
      <para>Select "File->Open" and locate the file of your measurement of the spectrum. Press Open and ensure that the graph that appears is what is expected.</para>
      <para>As interferometers are in general not band-limited, the Fourier basis is likely the best for processing in this instance. Ensure "Advanced->Basis function:->Fourier" is selected. Furthermore for "Spectrum Start" and "Spectrum Stop" you should select the full range of measurement available. I.e. move your mouse on the plot to the left most data point and read off the x coordinate displayed in the statusbar at the bottom of the screen. Choose a value just above this (Else the program may look for a value that does not exist in your data set) for the "Spectrum Start". Similarly for "Spectrum Stop", choose a value just below that of the rightmost data point of the plot. For the best results, adjust the Spectrum Start and Stop values to correspond to the spectral peaks for transmission measurements or the spectral troughs for reflection measurements.</para>
      <para>For the "Zero Padding" value choose the smallest 2's exponent that is greater than the number of data points. E.g. if you have 1835 points select 11 as the value for zero padding (<inlineequation><mathphrase>2<superscript>10</superscript>=1024&lt;1835, 2<superscript>11</superscript>=2048&gt;1835</mathphrase></inlineequation>). Greater values are possible if finer resolution in the inverse domain is required; however, as this example uses the full data range it is unlikely that this will be required.</para>
      <para>For the "Offset" value select the maximum value of the spectrum.</para>
      <para>If the measurement was performed in transmission, then select "Properties->Transmission Measurement?". Otherwise leave this deselected. Similarly if the measurement was in decibels select "Properties->Data in dBs?", otherwise leave it deselected. It may be possible that the data is upside down due to measurement being normalised the wrong way around. In this case it can be corrected by selecting "Properties->Negate?", otherwise leave this deselected (It should be noted that if the data is upside down the troughs and peaks mentioned above will also be upside down and require aligning to what will appear as troughs for transmission and peaks for reflection). Press "Transform Spectrum".</para>
      <para>Examine the spectrum displayed. There should be a peak shown at the inverse of the periodicity of the (wavenumber based) spectrum. If this peak is broader than the peak at zero then there is chirp in the spectrum and you may want to analyse how much (in which case select "Advanced->Calculate Chirp?").</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2><title>Processing a set of measurements using batch processing</title>
      <para>Select one of the measurements that gives a good ability to determine the processing parameters (such as Start/Stop and Triangle Centre values) and process it normally as above. If you are happy with the parameters then select "Advanced->Batch Process Data?". If the offset is inconsistent you may want to select "Advanced->Autotrack Offset?" or "Advanced->Apply correction to window edges?". See their use <link linkend="base_edgecorr">above</link>.</para>
      <para>Press "File->Open" and type in a name for a configuration file and then press "New". For future use if you are going to reprocess the same set of data pressing "Apply" will load the existing configuration file without the need to repeat the following step.</para>
      <para>Choosing a variable that differs from file to file (e.g. time, orientation angle or temperature of the device), change the numerical spin button to a value that is the lower bound of this variable over the data set. Then press "Add another file" and select the data file that this value is associated with. Repeat with taking the next larger value each time (always selecting the value before the file as the value cannot be changed afterwards yet) until all files are present and then press "Save".</para>
      <para>From "Properties->Display Properties" change the font, size and labels for the axes (and potentially select multiple traces) as desired. With the resulting graph displayed it can be printed with "File->Print" or its data saved to a spreadsheet format with "File->Save".</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <glossary>
    <glossdiv><title>B</title>
      <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Batch Processing</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>Automatically running a process repeatedly on a number of different data sets. A batch (or configuration) file specifying the location of each piece of data and its relevnce to the whole is usually needed.</para></glossdef>
      </glossentry>
    </glossdiv>
    <glossdiv><title>C</title>
      <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Chirp</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>The change in periodicity of a signal over its duration/spectrum. Chirp is seen in nonlinearity in the phase and often described in terms of constituent orders; linear chirp being due to quadratic phase terms, quadratic chirp being due to cubic phase terms, etc.</para></glossdef>
      </glossentry>
    </glossdiv>
    <glossdiv><title>E</title>
      <glossentry>
        <glossterm>EPS</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>Encapsulated Postscript. An image file that is described by a set of vectors rather than the usual bitmap format. An advantage of vector graphics is that they can be scaled to arbitrary sizes without losing resolution.</para></glossdef>
      </glossentry>
    </glossdiv>
    <glossdiv><title>L</title>
      <glossentry>
        <glossterm>LaTEX</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>A professional typesetting program commonly used for publishing academic material.</para></glossdef>
      </glossentry>
    </glossdiv>
    <glossdiv><title>M</title>
      <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Multiple Scattering</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>When a signal reflects off more than one element prior to detection.</para></glossdef>
      </glossentry>
    </glossdiv>
    <glossdiv><title>O</title>
      <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Offset</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>The reference level to take as 100% transmission or reflection.</para></glossdef>
      </glossentry>
    </glossdiv>
    <glossdiv><title>S</title>
      <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Spectral Shadowing</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>When upstream elements remove a portion of the spectrum available to downstream elements.</para></glossdef>
      </glossentry>
    </glossdiv>
    <glossdiv><title>V</title>
      <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Visibility of Fringes</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>For a pure unmodulated sinusodal waveform, the visibility is defined as half of the peak to peak amplitude divided by the average value: <inlineequation><mathphrase>V=(max-min)/(max+min)</mathphrase></inlineequation>.</para></glossdef>
      </glossentry>
    </glossdiv>
    <glossdiv><title>Z</title>
      <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Zero Padding</glossterm>
        <glossdef><para>Adding zero values to either end of a data set prior to transformation. Extending the data set in this way provides a finer resolution in the inverse domain.</para></glossdef>
      </glossentry>
    </glossdiv>
  </glossary>
</article>
